# Mashaan Alshammari

Riyadh, Saudi Arabia mashaan.awad@outlook.com https://mashaan14.github.io/mashaan/ https://linkedin.com/in/mashaan

I am a machine learning researcher, working on graph clustering and deep learning problems. Previously, I held academic positions in an Australian institute and a Saudi university. I designed material for computer science at masters and undergraduate levels.

Last Updated: September 2023

#### **EDUCATION**

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Computer Science, The University of Sydney, Thesis title: "Graph Filtering and Automatic Parameter Selection for Efficient Spectral Clustering." 2017 - 2021Master of Science, Computer Science, King Fahd University of Petroleum and Minerals (KFUPM), Thesis title: "Human In-Place Action Recognition using Combination of Kinect Data Streams." 2013 - 2016

Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, University of Hail,

Second honors. 2005 - 2010

## SKILLS

Research & Development Authored +15 research papers. Communication English (fluent), Arabic (native).

Technical Python and Java programming, Python's ML libraries (scikit-learn, pytorch, seaborn), manim

Curriculum design Experience in designing computer science and data science courses according to Australian Qualifications

Framework (AQF) and Saudi Arabia's NCAAA.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## **CURRICULUM DEVELOPMENT COLLABORATOR**

Jul 2023 — Present Sydney, Australia

Sydney Polytechnic Institute

- Participated in curriculum development for a Master of Data Science and Bachelor of Computing.
- Designed the outline and planner documents for courses: Database Systems (U211), Cybersecurity and Information Assurance (U312), and Full-stack development (U322).

#### MACHINE LEARNING RESEARCHER

JUN 2022 — Present

Freelance

Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

- · Working on machine learning research with researchers from the University of Sydney and KFUPM.
- Our research focuses on Graph Convolutional Network (GCN) and Unsupervised Domain Adaptation (UDA).
- Designed experiments using python ML libraries (scikit-learn, pytorch, seaborn, and others).

#### ASSISTANT PROFESSOR

Sydney Polytechnic Institute

JAN 2021 — JUN 2022

University of Hail

Hail. Saudi Arabia

- Participated in curriculum design and lecturing for multiple graduate and undergraduate computer science courses.
- Adapted new teaching strategies to teach the following courses: data structures (ICS202), advanced database (ICS434), and machine learning for big data (CSAI510).

## **CURRICULUM DEVELOPMENT COLLABORATOR**

SEP 2020 — MAR 2021

Sydney, Australia

- Participated in curriculum development for a Master of Data Science.
- Designed lecture slides, assignments, practical sessions, and exams for courses: Database Systems and Infrastructure (MDS604), Mathematics for data science (MDS602), and Artificial Intelligence and Innovation (MDS607).

SYSTEM ENGINEER AUG 2010 — MAY 2012 SABIC Jubail, Saudi Arabia

- In charge of securing and maintaining the plant network components.
- · Upgraded obsolete network components during online operation.

INTERN JUN 2009 — JAN 2010 Saudi Aramco Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

- · Completed cooperative training at EXPEC ARC as a member of Computational Modeling Team.
- Developed a GUI interface populating the simulator output, large text files, into a database.

# Mashaan Alshammari

Last Updated: September 2023

Riyadh, Saudi Arabia mashaan.awad@outlook.com https://mashaan14.github.io/mashaan/ https://linkedin.com/in/mashaan

## SELECTED GITHUB PROJECTS

## VisionTransformer-MNIST

ViT, pytorch, Jupyter Notebook

- Implementation of the paper "An Image is Worth 16x16 Words: Transformers for Image Recognition at Scale", which was published by Google research.
- Vision transformers replaces CNNs as the preferred method for image classification.

#### **ADDA**

GANs, pytorch, Jupyter Notebook

- Implementation of the paper "Adversarial Discriminative Domain Adaptation", which was published in CVPR2017.
- ADDA uses GANs to perform unsupervised domain adaptation (UDA).

#### python-tutorials

python, scikit-learn, Jupyter Notebook

- A collection of notebooks on vectorization and graphs in python.
- Vectorization refers to the style of coding where operations are applied to the whole array instead of individual elements.

#### manim

python, manim

- Manim is a python library to animate technical concepts.
- I used manim to visualize the behavior of some numpy and pytorch functions.

## **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS**

- Mashaan Alshammari, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Graph Construction using Principal Axis Trees for Simple Graph Convolution.", arXiv:2302.12000, 2023.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Random projection forest initialization for graph convolutional networks.", arXiv:2302.12001, 2023.
- Mashaan Alshammari, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Random projection tree similarity metric for SpectralNet.", Array, 2023.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "The Effect of Points Dispersion on the k-nn Search in Random Projection Forests.", **IEEE Access**, 2022.
- Mashaan Alshammari, John Stavrakakis, Masahiro Takatsuka: "A Parameter-Free Graph Reduction for Spectral Clustering and Spectralnet.", Array, 2022.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, John Stavrakakis, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Refining a k-nearest neighbor graph for a computationally efficient spectral clustering.", **Pattern Recognition**, 2021.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Approximate spectral clustering density-based similarity for noisy datasets.", **Pattern Recognition Letters**, 2019.
- Mashaan Alshammari, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Approximate spectral clustering with eigenvector selection and self-tuned k.", Pattern Recognition Letters, 2019.

## SELECTED ACTIVITIES

# Journal Reviewer

- Pattern Recognition Journal
- Information Sciences Journal
- Expert Systems with Applications Journal

## **Conference Organization**

- <u>Program committee</u>, 30th International Conference on Neural Information Processing (ICONIP2023), Changsha, China, November 20-23, 2023.
- <u>Technical Program Committee</u>, 7th International Conference on Data Science and Machine Learning Applications (CDMA2022), Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, March 1-3, 2022.